Intel(R) Master FLB file format change
======================================
March 6, 2012

Contents
========
- OVERVIEW
- CUSTOMER SUPPORT
- LEGAL


Overview
========
The Master FLB (BootIMG.FLB) file format has changed to allow using four part
Device IDs when necessary to distinguish the correct NVM image for a device.
All utilities and software are able to read older versions of the Master FLB.
However, you must update any utilities software you use to a more recent
version to use the new Master FLB. Please upgrade to the following versions (or
a more recent version):

- BootUtil, v. 1.3.5.xxx
- Intel(R) Proset for Windows* Device Manager, v. 17.1.xxx
- SMASH, v2-2.0.0.58

The current version can be downloaded at Intel's Network Products information
website: http://www.intel.com/network


CUSTOMER SUPPORT
================
- Main Intel web support site: http://support.intel.com

- Network products information: http://www.intel.com/network


LEGAL / DISCLAIMERS
===================
Copyright (C) 2012, Intel Corporation. All rights reserved.

Intel Corporation assumes no responsibility for errors or omissions in this
document. Nor does Intel make any commitment to update the information
contained herein.

Intel and the Intel logo are trademarks of Intel Corporation or its
subsidiaries in the U.S. and/or other countries.

*Other names and brands may be claimed as the property of others.

This software is furnished under license and may only be used or copied in
accordance with the terms of the license. The information in this manual is
furnished for informational use only, is subject to change without notice, and
should not be construed as a commitment by Intel Corporation. Intel Corporation
assumes no responsibility or liability for any errors or inaccuracies that may
appear in this document or any software that may be provided in association
with this document. Except as permitted by such license, no part of this
document may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any
form or by any means without the express written consent of Intel Corporation.
